A Guide to the Paul A. Weiss papers, Rockefeller University Faculty FA124
Rockefeller Archive Center
Paul A. Weiss papers, Rockefeller University Faculty
1922-1980
Rockefeller Archive Center
Weiss, Paul A.
Rockefeller University
Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
FA124
56.1 Cubic Feet 126 boxes.
Biographical/Historical note
Dr. Paul A. Weiss (1898-1989) was one of our nation's preeminent developmental biologists and professor emeritus at Rockefeller University. His research pioneered the understanding of the nervous system and how the brain operates. He was responsible for establishing the principles of cellular self-organization, in which cells that have been mixed randomly and reassembled from different organs can rebuild themselves into miniature copies of the donor organs without direction from a central source. In addition, he helped to prove that nerve cells replenish themselves to all parts of the body, and established new surgical methods for the repair of nerve tissue. He also showed that an embryo's organization and growth are determined by its physical and chemical environment, thus successfully challenging the long-held view that an embryo is organized by specific chemical compounds.
Weiss was born in Vienna in 1898, serving in the Austrian army in WWI. He later studied law and engineering at the University of Vienna. His interest in biology dates from the war and the reading of Darwin's On the Origin of Species while at the front. Thus his studies shifted to biology and pure research and he received his Ph.D. in biology in 1922.
Weiss spent the next decade conducting research for the Austrian Academy of Sciences, and completing postgraduate studies under a Rockefeller Foundation fellowship at various European science centers. In 1931 he emigrated to the United States and worked at Yale University as a Sterling Fellow. He lived the rest of his life in the United States, becoming a citizen in 1938.
He next went to the University of Chicago and conducted research there for the next 21 years. He came to the Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research in 1954. For the following decade he directed a new laboratory of developmental biology, specializing in research in wound healing, cancer and the development and repair of the nervous system. After 1964 he alternated research at Rockefeller with visiting professorships at other universities.
Weiss was a supportive teacher, influential lecturer and prodigious author, contributing more than 350 articles to professional and scientific journals and writing 11 books. His most influential works were the books Principles of Development: A Text in Experimental Embryology (1939) and The Science of Life (1973). He received many awards and honorary degrees in both the United States and Europe and was a scientific consultant to many governmental panels. He was a president of both the Society for Developmental Biology and the International Society for Cell Biology. In 1979, he received our nation's highest award for science, the National Medal of Science.
Dr. Weiss was also very concerned with the role of science in society, its basic research and humanistic values. He emphasized the "triple interplay" that experience, experiments and logic bring in promoting knowledge. In addition to promoting a positive perception of science among the general public, Dr. Weiss was also a very supportive teacher and advisor to students, and very anxious to see students of minority backgrounds have access to a scientific education.
Arrangement note
Arranged in chronological and alphabetical order.
Arranged into 15 series:1. Personal Files.2. Correspondence.3. Grants.4. Subject Files.5. Lectures.6. Administrative Files7. Manuscripts.8. Theses9. Laboratory Notes.10. Prints.11. Professional Societies.12. Article Reprints.13. Audio-Visual Materials.14. Memorabilia.15. Photographs.
File Plan note
Former Classification: I 450 W436
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Scope and Contents
Types of records include: personal files, correspondence, grant and subject files, administrative files, notes, reprints, audio-visual materials, photographs, and memorabilia.
Neurosciences; Biochemistry; Biology -- Research; Science -- Biological and Medical; Cell and biomolecular sciences
- Personal Files, 1922-1980; 1; 1.32 Cubic Feet Extent is approximate.
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes bibliography, citizenship papers, drawings, insurance papers, photographs, news clippings and scrapbook, letters, diplomas, military service records, obituaries and hospital records.
  Arrangement note
  Arranged in alphabetical order.
  - Bibliography of Works, 1921-1977 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Biographical File (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Biographical Material (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Citizenship Papers (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Confidential Salary and Appointments (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Cremation Records (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Drawings (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Grades, Diplomas and Military Service Records (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Guestbook (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Honors and Awards (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Honors and Honorary Degrees (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Hospital Records (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Insurance Papers (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Letter from Nina (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Letters to Nina (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - National Medal of Science (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - News Items, 1950-1979 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Obituaries and Letters of Condolence (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Photographs (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Presidents (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Portraits (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Postcards (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Seventieth Birthday Letters (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Scrapbook (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Scrapbook (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Scrapbook (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1930-1980; 2; 18.04 Cubic Feet Extent is approximate.
  Includes both personal and professional correspondence.
  - "A" (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - "A" (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Abels, Janice (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Abels, Janice (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Academic Press, Inc. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Adams, W. C. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Advisory Council (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Advisory Council (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Advisory Council (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Allison, Donna R. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Alpach, Austria (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Alstadter, Judith (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Ambrus, Julian (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - American Institute of Biological Sciences (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - American Philosophical Society (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - American Philosophical Society (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - American Philosophical Society (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - American Scientist (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - American Society for Cell Biology (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - American Society for Cell Biology (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - American Society for Cell Biology (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - American Society for Cybernetics (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - American Society of Zoologists (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Amprino, Rodolfo (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Amsterdam (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Andres, Gert (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Angyan, Andre J. (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Annicus Beads (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Arora, Harbans (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Association for Research in Nervous and Mental Disease (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Assorted Articles (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Austro-American Institute of Education (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Austro-American Institute of Education (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Awards (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Axonal Flow (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - "B" (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - "B" (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - "B" (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - "B" (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - "B" (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Beecher, Henry K. (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Benjamin, Edward B. (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Bergner, Per-Erick E. (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Bermuda Biological Station for Research (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Bessis, Marcel C. (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Biomedical Sciences at Texas Medical Center (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Biondi, Robert J. (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Biorheology (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Bircher, Franklin (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Bloom, William (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Bock, Albert (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Book Reviews (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Book Reviews (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Book Reviews (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Brachel, Jean (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Brain Research (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Brewer, Carl R. (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Bronk, Detlev W. (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - "C" (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - "C" (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - "C" (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - "C" (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Campbell, Frank L. (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Campbell, Richard D. (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Campbell, Richard D. (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Cebra, John J. (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Cell Therapy (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Chase, Elizabeth (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Chelsea Publishing (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Chicago (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Club of Rome (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Congress of Zoology (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Congress of Zoology (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Congress of Zoology (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Congressional Record (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Cosmo Club (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Coulombre, Alfred J. (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Council of Europe (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Cournand, Andre (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - "D" (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - "D" (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - "D" (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - "D" (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Dag Hammerskjold Fellowship (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Dahlstrom, Annica (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Danielli, Janis and Mary (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Data on Microphages (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - David, George (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Desmedt, J. E. (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Dethier, Vincent (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - "E" (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - "E" (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - "E" (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - "E" (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - Ebert, James (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - Eccles, John (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Edds, Rac V. (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Edelman, Gerald M. (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Ekistic Month (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Elkana, Yehuda (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Elsevier (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - "F" (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - "F" (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - "F" (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - "F" (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Fell, Honor B. (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Finckh, Ernst S. (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Fliedner, Theodor M. (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Fraser, Ronald (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Frensham Group (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Frensham Group (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Frensham Group (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Frensham Group (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Frensham Group (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - Frensham Pond Conference, 1967 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Frensham Pond Conference, 1967 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Fromm, Jacob E. (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Futura Publishing Company (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Futura Publishing Company (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - "G" (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - "G" (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - "G" (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - "G" (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - Gaillard, Peter (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Gerdy, James (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Goodfield, June (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Graduate School of Biomedics (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Grafstein, Bernice (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Grimburg, Gustaf (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - "H" (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - "H" (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - "H" (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - "H" (Box 17, Folder 10)
  - "H" (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Haas, Hermann (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Hackbell, Anna (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Horvath, Steven M. (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Haddow, Sir Alexander (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Haddow, Sir Alexander (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Hafner Publishing Company (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - Hamburger, Viktor (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - Haskins, Caryl P. (Box 18, Folder 9)
  - Horwitz, Louisa Grass (Box 18, Folder 10)
  - Hiscol, Helen (Box 18, Folder 11)
  - "I" (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - "I" (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Ingle, Dwight J. (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Inhelder, Barbel (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Institut de la Vie (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Institut de la Vie (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Institute for the Advancement of Medical Communication (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - Institute for the Advancement of Medical Communication (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - Interinstitutional Cell Research Organization (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - International Cell Research Organization (Box 19, Folder 10)
  - International Community College (Box 19, Folder 11)
  - International Conference on the Unity of the Sciences (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - International Conference on the Unity of the Sciences (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - International Institute of Embryology (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - International Journal of the Neurosciences (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - International Life Science Institute (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - International Life Science Institute (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - International Life Science Institute (Box 20, Folder 7)
  - International Science Foundation (Box 20, Folder 8)
  - "J" (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - "J" (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - "J-K" (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - "J-K" (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - Jaim-Etcheverry, Guillermo (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - Jaki, Stanley (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - Journal of Biophysical and Biochemical Cytology (Box 21, Folder 7)
  - Journal of Experimental Zoology (Box 21, Folder 8)
  - Journal of Theoretical Biology (Box 21, Folder 9)
  - Jung, Richard (Box 21, Folder 10)
  - "K" (Box 21, Folder 11)
  - "K" (Box 21, Folder 12)
  - Kalnitsky, George (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - Kavanau, Julian Lee (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - Kavanau, Julian Lee (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - Kavanau, Julian Lee (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - Kavanau, Julian Lee (Box 22, Folder 5)
  - Kemp, Norman E. (Box 22, Folder 6)
  - Knight, Douglas (Box 22, Folder 7)
  - Koestler, Arthur (Box 22, Folder 8)
  - "L" (Box 23, Folder 1)
  - "L" (Box 23, Folder 2)
  - "L" (Box 23, Folder 3)
  - "L" (Box 23, Folder 4)
  - Laboratory Personnel "D-I" (Box 23, Folder 5)
  - Laboratory Personnel "D-I" (Box 23, Folder 6)
  - Laboratory Personnel "J-L" (Box 23, Folder 7)
  - Laboratory Personnel "J-L" (Box 23, Folder 8)
  - Laszlo, Ervin (Box 24, Folder 1)
  - Laszlo, Ervin (Box 24, Folder 2)
  - Lecomte du Nouy Foundation (Box 24, Folder 3)
  - Lecomte du Nouy Foundation (Box 24, Folder 4)
  - Lederberg, Joshua (Box 24, Folder 5)
  - Lenneberg, Elizabeth (Box 24, Folder 6)
  - Leopoldina (Box 24, Folder 7)
  - Leopoldina, 1970 March 17 (Box 24, Folder 8)
  - Levy, Martin J. (Box 24, Folder 9)
  - Lorenz, Konrad (Box 24, Folder 10)
  - Lyser, Kay (Box 24, Folder 11)
  - "M" (Box 25, Folder 1)
  - "M" (Box 25, Folder 2)
  - "M" (Box 25, Folder 3)
  - "M" (Box 25, Folder 4)
  - "M" (Box 25, Folder 5)
  - "M" (Box 25, Folder 6)
  - Marine Biological Laboratory (Box 26, Folder 1)
  - Mascona, Aron (Box 26, Folder 2)
  - Matoltsy, A. Gedeon (Box 26, Folder 3)
  - Mayer, Clara (Box 26, Folder 4)
  - Mayor, Donald (Box 26, Folder 5)
  - Mayr, Robert (Box 26, Folder 6)
  - Max-Planck Institute (Box 26, Folder 7)
  - McKinley, Heide Marie (Box 26, Folder 8)
  - Medawar, Peter B. (Box 26, Folder 9)
  - Medin, Virginia P. (Box 26, Folder 10)
  - Meeker, Joseph W. (Box 26, Folder 11)
  - Mel, Howard C. (Box 26, Folder 12)
  - Merton, Robert (Box 26, Folder 13)
  - Mesarovic, Mihajlo (Box 26, Folder 14)
  - Meyer, Jean-Paul (Box 26, Folder 15)
  - Mills, Marcia (Box 26, Folder 16)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 27, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 27, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 27, Folder 3)
  - Mokerjee, Sivatosh (Box 27, Folder 4)
  - Morot, Sir Edward (Box 27, Folder 5)
  - Motion Pictures (Box 27, Folder 6)
  - Mt. Sinai School of Medicine (Box 27, Folder 7)
  - Muller, Gert (Box 27, Folder 8)
  - Mytilineou, Catherine (Box 27, Folder 9)
  - "N" (Box 27, Folder 10)
  - "N" (Box 27, Folder 11)
  - "N" (Box 28, Folder 1)
  - "N" (Box 28, Folder 2)
  - National Academy of Sciences (Box 28, Folder 3)
  - Naples Station (Box 28, Folder 4)
  - Naples Station (Box 28, Folder 5)
  - Naples Station (Box 28, Folder 6)
  - Naples Station (Box 28, Folder 7)
  - Naples Station (Box 29, Folder 1)
  - National Institutes of Health (Box 29, Folder 2)
  - National Library of Medicine (Box 29, Folder 3)
  - National Paraplegia Foundation (Box 29, Folder 4)
  - National Science Foundation (Box 29, Folder 5)
  - National Science Foundation (Box 29, Folder 6)
  - Newell, Ellen K. (Box 29, Folder 7)
  - Neurons (Box 29, Folder 8)
  - Neuroscience Research Program (Box 29, Folder 9)
  - Neuroscience Research Program (Box 29, Folder 10)
  - Neuroscience Research Program (Box 30, Folder 1)
  - Neuroscience Research Program (Box 30, Folder 2)
  - Neuroscience Research Program (Box 30, Folder 3)
  - New York Academy of Sciences (Box 30, Folder 4)
  - "O" (Box 30, Folder 5)
  - Organisation for Economic Cooperation and Development (Box 30, Folder 6)
  - Ozbekhan, Hasan (Box 30, Folder 7)
  - "P" (Box 30, Folder 8)
  - "P" (Box 31, Folder 1)
  - "P" (Box 31, Folder 2)
  - "P" (Box 31, Folder 3)
  - "P" (Box 31, Folder 4)
  - "P" (Box 31, Folder 5)
  - "P" (Box 31, Folder 6)
  - Pacific Science Center (Box 32, Folder 1)
  - Pillai, P. Alyappan (Box 32, Folder 2)
  - Pergamon Press (Box 32, Folder 3)
  - Permission Letters (Box 32, Folder 4)
  - Personal (Box 32, Folder 5)
  - Perspectives in Biology and Medicine (Box 32, Folder 6)
  - Poole, Brian (Box 32, Folder 7)
  - Positions Wanted (Box 32, Folder 8)
  - Prachinsky, Hubert (Box 32, Folder 9)
  - President's Advisory Committee (Box 32, Folder 10)
  - Publications, 1955-1956 (Box 32, Folder 11)
  - "Q" (Box 32, Folder 12)
  - Quarterly Review of Biology (Box 32, Folder 13)
  - "R" (Box 33, Folder 1)
  - "R" (Box 33, Folder 2)
  - "R" (Box 33, Folder 3)
  - "R" (Box 33, Folder 4)
  - "R" (Box 33, Folder 5)
  - "R" (Box 33, Folder 6)
  - "R" (Box 34, Folder 1)
  - "R" (Box 34, Folder 2)
  - Rabes, Hartmut (Box 34, Folder 3)
  - Rahmann, Heinrich (Box 34, Folder 4)
  - Randall, Sir John (Box 34, Folder 5)
  - Ransom, Harry H. (Box 34, Folder 6)
  - Ransom, Harry H. (Box 34, Folder 7)
  - Ranzi, Silvio (Box 34, Folder 8)
  - Rasmussen, Grant L. (Box 34, Folder 9)
  - Ratliff, Merry (Box 34, Folder 10)
  - Recruiting (Box 34, Folder 11)
  - Research Grant (Box 35, Folder 1)
  - Retirement (Box 35, Folder 2)
  - Rev, Lyvia (Box 35, Folder 3)
  - Rhea, Robert P. (Box 35, Folder 4)
  - Riedl, Rupert (Box 35, Folder 5)
  - Robbins, Elliott (Box 35, Folder 6)
  - Robbins, Norman (Box 35, Folder 7)
  - Rockefeller Foundation (Box 35, Folder 8)
  - Rockefeller University (Box 35, Folder 9)
  - RU Miscellaneous (Box 35, Folder 10)
  - RU Press (Box 35, Folder 11)
  - Rosenbaum, Robert M. (Box 35, Folder 12)
  - Rosenberg, Murray (Box 35, Folder 13)
  - Rueff, Jacques (Box 35, Folder 14)
  - Runnstrom, John and Vera (Box 35, Folder 15)
  - "S" (Box 36, Folder 1)
  - "S" (Box 36, Folder 2)
  - "S" (Box 36, Folder 3)
  - "S" (Box 36, Folder 4)
  - "S" (Box 36, Folder 5)
  - Saturday Review (Box 37, Folder 1)
  - Schiller, Hillel (Box 37, Folder 2)
  - Schiller, Hillel (Box 37, Folder 3)
  - Science (Box 37, Folder 4)
  - Scientific American (Box 37, Folder 5)
  - Scott, Bruce (Box 37, Folder 6)
  - Scriven, Skip (Box 37, Folder 7)
  - Seilarn-Aspang, Friedrich (Box 37, Folder 8)
  - Seilarn-Aspang, Friedrich (Box 37, Folder 9)
  - Seitelberger, Franz (Box 37, Folder 10)
  - Seitz, Frederick (Box 37, Folder 11)
  - Sengel, Philippe (Box 38, Folder 1)
  - Shockley, William (Box 38, Folder 2)
  - Shockley, William (Box 38, Folder 3)
  - Sigma XI RU Chapter (Box 38, Folder 4)
  - Smithsonian (Box 38, Folder 5)
  - Smythias, John R. (Box 38, Folder 6)
  - Society for Developmental Biology (Box 38, Folder 7)
  - Society for Neuroscience (Box 38, Folder 8)
  - Southern Illinois University Conference, 1976 (Box 38, Folder 9)
  - Springer-Verlag Publishing Company (Box 38, Folder 10)
  - Stark, Lawrence (Box 38, Folder 11)
  - Stephenson, Robert (Box 39, Folder 1)
  - Stich, Hans F. (Box 39, Folder 2)
  - Strehler, Bernard L. (Box 39, Folder 3)
  - Stulman, Julius (Box 39, Folder 4)
  - Svetlov, P. B. (Box 39, Folder 5)
  - Sweden (Box 39, Folder 6)
  - "T" (Box 39, Folder 7)
  - "T" (Box 39, Folder 8)
  - "T-U" (Box 39, Folder 9)
  - Taylor, A. Cecil (Box 40, Folder 1)
  - Taylor, A. Cecil (Box 40, Folder 2)
  - Taylor, A. Cecil (Box 40, Folder 3)
  - Teleki, Charles and Vera (Box 40, Folder 4)
  - Texas A (Box 40, Folder 5)
  - Throbbing Cells (Box 40, Folder 6)
  - Tissue Culture Association (Box 40, Folder 7)
  - Toro, Imra (Box 40, Folder 8)
  - Tonutti, Emil (Box 40, Folder 9)
  - Toulmin, Stephen and June (Box 40, Folder 10)
  - Travel, 1967-1977 (Box 40, Folder 11)
  - Travel Abroad, 1959-1976 (Box 40, Folder 12)
  - "U-V" (Box 41, Folder 1)
  - "U-V" (Box 41, Folder 2)
  - University Affairs (Box 41, Folder 3)
  - University Affairs (Box 41, Folder 4)
  - University of Chicago Press (Box 41, Folder 5)
  - Unity of Culture Conference, 1967 (Box 41, Folder 6)
  - University of Texas (Box 41, Folder 7)
  - University of Texas (Box 41, Folder 8)
  - University of Texas, 1964-1965 (Box 41, Folder 9)
  - University of Texas Doctor's Club (Box 41, Folder 10)
  - University of Texas Medical School (Box 41, Folder 11)
  - University of Texas News and Information Service (Box 42, Folder 1)
  - University of Texas Science Conference (Box 42, Folder 2)
  - "V" (Box 42, Folder 3)
  - "V-W" (Box 42, Folder 4)
  - "V-W" (Box 42, Folder 5)
  - Van Leer Foundation, 1966 (Box 42, Folder 6)
  - Van Leer Foundation, 1966 (Box 42, Folder 7)
  - Van Leer Foundation, 1966 (Box 42, Folder 8)
  - "W" (Box 42, Folder 9)
  - "W" (Box 43, Folder 1)
  - "W" (Box 43, Folder 2)
  - "W-Z" (Box 43, Folder 3)
  - Wasserman, Gerhard D. (Box 43, Folder 4)
  - Welch Foundation (Box 43, Folder 5)
  - West, Wesley (Box 43, Folder 6)
  - Whaley, W. Gordon (Box 43, Folder 7)
  - Whyte, Lancelot L. (Box 43, Folder 8)
  - Weerdeman, MW (Box 43, Folder 9)
  - Wolff, Etienne (Box 44, Folder 1)
  - World Book Encyclopedia (Box 44, Folder 2)
  - Wrba, Heinrich (Box 44, Folder 3)
  - Willier, Benjamin (Box 44, Folder 4)
  - Warren, Katherine B. (Box 44, Folder 5)
  - Weiss, George (Box 44, Folder 6)
  - Xerox (Box 44, Folder 7)
  - "Y" (Box 44, Folder 8)
  - "Y-Z" (Box 44, Folder 9)
  - "Z" (Box 44, Folder 10)
  - Zenker, Wolfgang (Box 44, Folder 11)
  - Zuber, Corinna (Box 44, Folder 12)
  - Zurich Conference, 1976 (Box 44, Folder 13)
  - Zvilna, Jekabs (Box 44, Folder 14)
- Grants, 1950-1960s; 3; 0.88 Cubic Feet Extent is approximate.
  Includes grant applications, general information and financial disbursements. Other grant material can be found in Series 6, Administrative Files.
  Arranged in alphabetical order by funding organization, then numerically by grant number.
  - Faith Fund RU Account #1101 (Box 45, Folder 1)
  - Faith Fund RU Account #1950 (Box 45, Folder 2)
  - NIH Grant CA 06375-03 (Box 45, Folder 3)
  - NIH Grant CA 08704-01 (Box 45, Folder 4)
  - NIH Grant NB 07348 (Box 45, Folder 5)
  - NTH Grant NB-07348-02 (Box 46, Folder 1)
  - NIH Grant NB-07348-03 (Box 46, Folder 2)
  - NIH Grant Budget, 1968-1970 (Box 46, Folder 3)
  - NLM Grant, 1971-1972 (Box 46, Folder 4)
  - NSF Grant Application 75-03244 (Box 46, Folder 5)
  - NSF Grant GB-31143 (Box 46, Folder 6)
  - Public Health Service Grant NS-07348-03 (Box 46, Folder 7)
  - Site Visit-NIH (Box 46, Folder 8)
  - Withdrawn NIH Grant, 1971-1972 (Box 46, Folder 9)
- Subject Files, 1940-1976; 4; 0.88 Cubic Feet Extent is approximate.